I don't know why, but I'm continually amazed to think
لا أعرف لماذا، ولكنني أندهش باستمرار حين أفكر
that two and a half billion of us around the world
أن مليارين ونصف المليار منا حول العالم
are connected to each other through the Internet
متصلون ببعضنا البعض عبر الإنترنت
and that at any point in time
و أن في أي لحظة زمنية
more than 30 percent of the world's population
أكثر من 30 في المائة من سكان العالم
can go online to learn, to create and to share.
يمكنهم أن يدخلوا على الإنترنت للتعلم والإنشاء والمشاركة.
And the amount of time each of us is spending doing all of this
ومقدار الوقت الذي يقضيه كل منا في القيام بكل هذا
is also continuing to go grow.
يتزايد باستمرار أيضاً.
A recent study showed
أظهرت دراسة حديثة
that the young generation alone
أن جيل الشباب لوحده
is spending over eight hours a day online.
يقضي أكثر من ثمانية ساعات في اليوم على الإنترنت.
As the parent of a nine-year-old girl,
وكأب لفتاة عمرها تسع سنوات،
that number seems awfully low.
ذلك الرقم يبدو قليلا بشكل مروع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But just as the Internet has opened up the world for each and every one of us,
ولكن تماما مثلما فتحت الإنترنت العالم لكل واحد منا،
it has also opened up each and every one of us to the world.
فتحت كذلك كل واحد منا وجميعنا للعالم.
And increasingly, the price we're being asked to pay
و بتزايد الثمن الذي يتطلب منا دفعه
for all of this connectedness
مقابل كل هذه التواصلية
is our privacy.
هي الخصوصية.
Today, what many of us would love to believe
واليوم، الكثير منا يود أن يعتقد
is that the Internet is a private place; it's not.
أن الإنترنت هو مكان خاص؛ هو ليس كذلك.
And with every click of the mouse and every touch of the screen,
ومع كل نقرة فأرة وكل لمسة للشاشة،
we are like Hansel and Gretel
نكون مثل هانسيل وجريتيل
leaving breadcrumbs of our personal information
نترك فتات خبز معلوماتنا الشخصية
everywhere we travel through the digital woods.
في كل مكان نعبره في الغابات الرقمية.
We are leaving our birthdays, our places of residence,
نترك تواريخ ميلادنا وأماكن سكننا
our interests and preferences,
ومصالحنا وتفضيلاتنا
our relationships,
وعلاقاتنا
our financial histories, and on and on it goes.
وتاريخنا المالي إلى ما إلى ذلك.
Now don't get me wrong,
ولا تفهموني خطأ،
I'm not for one minute suggesting that sharing data is a bad thing.
أنا لست أوحي لدقيقة أن مشاركة البيانات أمر سيء.
In fact, when I know the data that's being shared
في الواقع، حين أعرف البيانات التي تتم مشاركتها
and I'm asked explicitly for my consent,
وتطلب مني موافقتي بوضوح،
I want some sites to understand my habits.
أريد من بعض المواقع أن تفهم عاداتي.
It helps them suggest books for me to read
يساعدها ذلك على اقتراح كتب علي لأقرأها
or movies for my family to watch
أو أفلام لتشاهدها عائلتي
or friends for us to connect with.
أو أصدقاء نتصل بهم.
But when I don't know and when I haven't been asked,
ولكن عندما لا أعرف وعندما لا يستأذن مني،
that's when the problem arises.
هناك تبدأ المشاكل.
It's a phenomenon on the Internet today
إنها ظاهرة على شبكة الإنترنيت اليوم
called behavioral tracking,
تدعى التعقب السلوكي،
and it is very big business.
وهي مجال ربحي ضخم جدا.
In fact, there's an entire industry formed
وفي الواقع، هناك صناعة كاملة تتشكل
around following us through the digital woods
حول متابعتنا بواسطة الغابات الرقمية
and compiling a profile on each of us.
وتجميع ملف تعريفي عن كل واحد منا.
And when all of that data is held,
وحين يحصلون على كل البيانات،
they can do almost whatever they want with it.
يمكنهم تقريبا أن يفعلوا بها ما يشاؤون.
This is an area today that has very few regulations
وهذا مجال تقل فيه القوانين اليوم
and even fewer rules.
وتقل القواعد.
Except for some of the recent announcements here in the United States and in Europe,
باستثناء بعض الإعلانات التي صدرت مؤخرا هنا في الولايات المتحدة وفي أوروبا،
it's an area of consumer protection that's almost entirely naked.
وهو مجال تقريبا مكشوف كليا في حماية المستهلكين.
So let me expose this lurking industry a little bit further.
لذلك اسمحوا لي أن أفضح هاته الصناعة المتخفية قليلا أكثر.
The visualization you see forming behind me is called Collusion
المرئيات التي ترونها تتشكل خلفي تدعى "تواطؤ"
and it's an experimental browser add-on
وهي إضافة برمجية تجريبية للمتصفحات
that you can install in your Firefox browser
يمكنكم تثبيتها في متصفح فايرفوكس الخاص بكم
that helps you see where your Web data is going and who's tracking you.
وتساعدكم على معرفة حيثما تذهب بيانات الويب الخاصة بكم ومن يتعقبكم.
The red dots you see up there
النقاط الحمراء التي تشاهدونها في الأعلى هناك
are sites that are behavioral tracking
هي المواقع التي تتعقب السلوكيات
that I have not navigated to, but are following me.
وهي مواقع لم أتصفحها، لكنها تتعقبتي.
The blue dots are the sites that I've actually navigated directly to.
النقاط الزرقاء هي المواقع التي قد دخلت إليها فعلا مباشرة.
And the gray dots are sites that are also tracking me,
والنقاط الرمادية هي المواقع التي تتعقبني كذلك،
but I have no idea who they are.
ولكن ليست لدى أي فكرة عما هي.
All of them are connected, as you can see,
جميعها مترابطة كما ترون،
to form a picture of me on the Web.
لتشكيل صورة عني على شبكة الإنترنت.
And this is my profile.
وهذا هو ملفي التعريفي.
So let me go from an example to something very specific and personal.
لذلك اسمحوا لي أن انتقل من مثال إلى شيء محدد وشخصي جداً.
I installed Collusion in my own laptop two weeks ago
قمت بتثبيت "التواطؤ" على حاسبي المحمول قبل أسبوعين
and I let it follow me around for what was a pretty typical day.
وسمحت له بتتبعي في يوم اعتيادي.
Now like most of you,
الآن مثل معظمكم،
I actually start my day going online and checking email.
ابدأ يومي في الواقع بالدخول على الإنترنت والتحقق من بريدي الإلكتروني.
I then go to a news site, look for some headlines.
ثم أذهب إلى موقع أخبار فأنظر إلى بعض العناوين.
And in this particular case I happened to like one of them
وفي هذه الحالة بالذات حدث وأعجبني أحدها
on the merits of music literacy in schools
يتعلق بمزايا محو أمية الموسيقى في المدارس
and I shared it over a social network.
فقمت بمشاركته عن طريق شبكة اجتماعية.
Our daughter then joined us at the breakfast table,
ثم انضمت ابنتنا على مائدة الإفطار،
and I asked her, "Is there an emphasis on music literacy in your school?"
فسألتها، "هل هناك تركيز على محو أمية الموسيقى في مدرستكم؟"
And she, of course, naturally as a nine-year-old,
فقالت، وبطبيعة الحال، لكونها في التاسعة من عمرها،
looked at me and said quizzically, "What's literacy?"
نظرت إلي وقالت بتساؤل، "ما هو محو الأمية؟"
So I sent her online, of course, to look it up.
وبالتالي أرسلتها إلى شبكة الإنترنت بطبيعة الحال لتبحث عنها.
Now let me stop here.
الآن اسمحوا لي أن أتوقف هنا.
We are not even two bites into breakfast
لم نتجاوز حتى لقمتين من طعام الإفطار
and there are already nearly 25 sites that are tracking me.
وهناك بالفعل ما يقرب من 25 موقعا يتعقبني.
I have navigated to a total of four.
وقد أبحرت ضمن أربعة منهم.
So let me fast-forward through the rest of my day.
لذلك اسمحوا لي أن أتقدم بسرعة عبر بقية يومي.
I go to work, I check email,
أذهب إلى العمل، أتحقق من بريدي الإلكتروني،
I log onto a few more social sites, I blog,
أدخل إلى بضعة مواقع إجتماعية أخرى وأدون
I check more news reports, I share some of those news reports,
وأطلع على المزيد من التقارير الإخبارية وأشارك بعضا من تلك التقارير الإخبارية،
I go look at some videos,
أذهب لأطلع على بعض مقاطع الفيديو،
pretty typical day -- in this case, actually fairly pedantic --
يوم عادي جدا -- في هذه الحالة، يوم متحذلق بوضوح --
and at the end of the day, as my day winds down,
وفي نهاية اليوم، بانتهاء كل شيء،
look at my profile.
انظروا إلى ملف التعريف الخاص بي.
The red dots have exploded.
وقد انفجرت النقاط الحمراء.
The gray dots have grown exponentially.
وتضاعفت النقاط الحمراء أسيا.
All in all, there's over 150 sites
وبشكل عام، هناك ما يزيد عن 150 موقعا
that are now tracking my personal information,
تتبع معلوماتي الشخصية الآن،
most all of them without my consent.
أغلبها من دون موافقتي.
I look at this picture and it freaks me out.
أنظر إلى هذه الصورة فترعبني.
This is nothing. I am being stalked across the Web.
هذا لا شيء. تتم مطاردتي عبر الإنترنت.
And why is this happening?
ولماذا يحدث هذا؟
Pretty simple -- it's huge business.
بكل بساطة -- هو مجال ربحي هائل.
The revenue of the top handful of companies in this space
إيرادات حفنة من أكبر الشركات في هذا المجال
is over 39 billion dollars today.
هي أكثر من 39 مليار دولار اليوم.
And as adults, we're certainly not alone.
وكبالغين، نحن بالتأكيد لسنا الوحيدين.
At the same time I installed my own Collusion profile,
وفي الوقت نفسه الذي ركبت ملف التواطؤ التعريفي الخاص بي،
I installed one for my daughter.
ركبت واحدا لابنتي.
And on one single Saturday morning, over two hours on the Internet,
وفي صباح يوم سبت، بعد ساعتين على الإنترنت،
here's her Collusion profile.
ها هو ملف تواطؤها التعريفي.
This is a nine-year-old girl
هذه فتاة تبلغ من العمر تسع سنوات
navigating to principally children's sites.
تتنقل أساسا بين مواقع الأطفال.
I move from this, from freaked out to enraged.
أنتقل من هذا، من الفزع إلى الغضب.
This is no longer me being a tech pioneer or a privacy advocate;
لم يعد الأمر يتعلق بكوني رائد تقنية أو مدافعا عن الخصوصية؛
this is me being a parent.
هذا أنا كأب.
Imagine in the physical world
تخيلوا في العالم المادي
if somebody followed our children around with a camera and a notebook
إذا كان شخص ما يتبع أطفالنا يكاميرا وجهاز كمبيوتر محمول
and recorded their every movement.
ويسجلون كل تحركاتهم.
I can tell you, there isn't a person in this room that would sit idly by.
أستطيع أن أقول لكم، أنه ليس هناك أي شخص في هذه القاعة سيقف مكتوف الأيدي.
We'd take action. It may not be good action, but we would take action.
سوف نقدم على مبادرة. قد لا تكون مبادرة جيدة، لكننا سنقدم عليها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We can't sit idly by here either.
لا يمكن أن نجلس مكتوفي الأيدي هنا كذلك.
This is happening today.
وهذا يحدث اليوم.
Privacy is not an option,
الخصوصية ليس خياراً،
and it shouldn't be the price we accept
ولا ينبغي أن تكون الثمن الذي نقبله
for just getting on the Internet.
لمجرد الوصول إلى الإنترنت.
Our voices matter and our actions matter even more.
أصواتنا تهم وأفعالنا تهم أكثر.
Today we've launched Collusion.
لقد أطلقنا اليوم برنامج "التواطؤ".
You can download it, install it in Firefox,
يمكنك تحميله وتثبيته في الفايرفوكس،
to see who is tracking you across the Web
لرؤية من يتعقبكم عبر الويب
and following you through the digital woods.
ويتبعك عبر الغابات الرقمية.
Going forward, all of our voices need to be heard.
للمضي قدما، جميع أصواتنا يجب أن تسمع.
Because what we don't know can actually hurt us.
لأن ما لا نعرفه يمكنه فعلا أن يؤذينا.
Because the memory of the Internet is forever.
لأن ذاكرة الإنترنت تدوم إلى الأبد.
We are being watched.
نحن مراقبون.
It's now time for us to watch the watchers.
حان الوقت لنراقب المراقبين.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)